( MELANIE TAKES DEEP BREATH )
MELANIE : ( WHISPERS ) One , two , three , four ,
five , six , seven , eight , nine , ten ,
11,12,13,14,15 ,
16 , 17 , 18 , 19 , 20 ,
21 , 22 , 23 , 24 , 25 ,
26 , 27 , 28 , 29,30 ,
31 , 32 , 33 , 34 , 35 ,
36 , 37 , 38 , 39 , 40 ,
41 , 42 , 43 ...
( DOOR CLANKS OPEN )
( KLAXON HORN BLARES )
MAN : Transit , let 's go .
- Wakey-wakey , we 're on the move ! - ( BANGING ON DOORS )
Transit , let 's go .
Rise and shine , you friggin ' abortions . Let 's go .
- Transit ! - ( BANGING ON DOORS )
Wakey-wakey .
Transit !
Come on , you friggin ' abortions .
Good morning , Private Gallagher . Good morning , Private Devani .
- GALLAGHER : Head secured . - DEVANI : OK .
GALLAGHER : Limbs secured .
" Cuffs and straps to be verified manually and by line of sight . "
Nice going , shithead . Knows the drill better than you do .
( MAN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY )
MAN : Need some help here !
( INDISTINCT CHATTER )
Good morning , Sergeant Parks .
- Gallagher , keep your distance . - Sarge .
( DOOR CLANGS SHUT )
( DOOR OPENS )
- Good morning , Miss . - ALL : Good morning , Dr Selkirk .
DR SELKIRK : Quiet , please . Is that everyone ?
Let 's make a start .
The periodic table . Close your eyes and visualise it .
And open . Actinides . Anne .
Ac ... Actinium .
- Thorium . - DR SELKIRK : With numbers .
- Who knows the numbers ? - 89 , 90 .
- DR SELKIRK : Yes . Next , Peter . - PETER : Uranium . 92 .
Protactinium , then uranium . Kenny ?
- Cobalt ? - DR SELKIRK : Actinides .
We 're on row seven .
( WHISPERS ) Neptunium .
- Neptunium . - DR SELKIRK : Number ?
Half a mark . Switch to period four . Anyone ?
19 , potassium . 20 , calcium . 21 , scandium ...
Earth metals ? Downwards from row two .
- Joe . - ( DOOR OPENS )
( DOOR CLANGS SHUT )
Morning , class .
ALL : Good morning , Miss Justineau .
- I hope you 're well , Miss Justineau . - I am very well . Thank you , Melanie .
Erm , I 'm done with the regression analysis . Thanks for filling in .
Ah , the periodic table . We haven 't really covered this yet .
Just data pairs . Names and numbers . Content is not really relevant , is it ?
Enjoy !
OK , I 've got chemical elements here .
- Oh . Lots and lots . - Can we have a story ?
Oh , yeah , that 's a great idea .
Then someone goes and tells Dr Caldwell and I 'm in the sweat box for a week .
We won 't tell . We promise .
We did stories last time .
Greek myths ? Then it counts as history .
All right . We 'll do one as a warm-up .
Now , where were we ?
Prometheus and Epimetheus . The war with the gods .
- Got it . Thank you , Melanie . - You 're very welcome , Miss Justineau .
" The gods do not forget .
" And by and by ,
" Zeus wanted to punish Epimetheus for his misdeeds ,
" so he fashioned a woman of clay and gave her the name Pandora .
" ' She who brings gifts . '
" Pandora opened up the box whereupon every plague and tribulation ,
" every misfortune and evil thing in the world came pouring out ,
" and they have afflicted mankind ever since ,
" all because of Pandora 's curiosity ... "
Good night , Private Dillon . Good night , Private Devani .
- Yeah . Sweet dreams , Cujo . - Don 't bloody talk to it .
( DOOR CLANGS SHUT )
" But then , Pandora peered into the box and found one more thing in the bottom .
" It was hope .
" And she lifted it in her hands and set it free .
" Hope ...
" ... is the good thing that makes you be able to stand all the bad things . "
But there isn 't anything bad here . Is there ?
Good night , black-and-white kitten .
( LIGHT SWITCH CLUNKS )
No .
I guess we do OK .
MELANIE : ( WHISPERS ) Good night , Miss Justineau .
( LIGHT SWITCHES CLUNK )
( KLAXON HORN BLARES )
MELANIE : ( WHISPERING ) 22 , 23 , 24 , 25 ,
26 , 27 , 28 , 29 , 30 , 31 ,
32 , 33 , 34 , 35 ,
36 , 37 , 38 , 39 , 40 ...
( FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING )
Hello , Melanie .
Hello , Dr Caldwell .
Did you solve the problem ?
Nobody broke into the room .
Lupin stole the jewels right at the start
when he pretended to check if they were still there .
Very good .
Here 's another . There 's a cat in a box .
It could be alive or it could be dead . Fifty-fifty .
- How would you find out ? - You 'd open the box and look inside .
Before that , when the box is closed , is the cat alive or dead ?
- Am I allowed to listen ? - No .
Or shake the box , or weigh it ? Or drill a hole in it ?
Nothing like that . It 's a logic problem .
( SIGHS ) I 'll have to think about it .
- What are you writing ? - Subject 's responses .
" Exquisite mimicry of observed behaviours . "
- Question mark . - What does that mean ?
That means the jury 's still out .
Give me a number from one to 20 .
- Thirteen . - Thank you .
- PARKS : Transit ! Let 's go ! - ( BANGING ON DOOR )
Rise and shine ! Come on , up you get ! Transit .
Come on , you friggin ' abortions . Let 's go !
Rise and shine ...
MAN : Look , we all agreed to do our bit of time here .
WOMAN : Three months , not six .
- Where 's Kenny ? Is Kenny coming to class ? - MAN : I know , but when we rotate ...
WOMAN : Should have fucking rotated in week 40 .
I should be in Beacon now .
MAN : Carlisle said the transport 's coming next week .
WOMAN : Yeah , he said that last week , didn 't he ?
" ' But no , ' the old man said . 'These are indeed your sailors ,
" ' turned into animals by the witch 's power . '
" ' By the gods ! ' Odysseus cried . 'If that were my fate
" ' and I brought down to a beast ,
" ' I would rather die by my own hand . " '
Wow , tough audience .
- Will Kenny come to class today ? - Not today .
Tomorrow ?
Here 's an idea .
I 'm gonna unlock your writing hands and take your trays out
and you 're gonna tell me a story .
- JOE : But we don 't know any stories . - Only the ones you 've told us .
That 's all right . I want you to make it up .
What should it be about ?
Anything you like , Melanie .
It 's up to you .
DILLON : Christ , look at the creepy little fuckers .
How can she stand being that close to them ?
She 's well fit , though , in 't she ?
( CHUCKLES )
All right , time 's up . Pencils down .
So , who would like to read their story out loud ?
Melanie . Start us off .
" Once upon a time , in ancient Greece , there was a woman .
" She was very beautiful ,
" the most beautiful and kind and clever and amazing woman in all the world .
" One day , she was walking in a forest
" when suddenly , she was attacked by a monster .
" It was a friggin ' abortion and it wanted to eat her .
" The woman was really brave .
" She fought and fought , but the monster was big and fierce .
" She couldn 't kill it . She broke her sword and her spear .
" The monster was about to eat her .
" But then a girl came running up .
" She was like Achilles because she couldn 't be hurt ,
" except in one place she kept secret .
" She fought the monster and killed it
" and cut off its head and went galumphing back .
" And the woman ...
" The woman said ,
" ' You are my special girl . You will always be with me
" ' and I 'll never , never let you go . '
" And they lived ... They lived happily together ever after . "
I 'm sorry .
( SNIFFLES )
Can I try again ?
Can I try again , please ?
- PARKS : No ! No fucking way ! No . - ( GASPS )
- I didn 't ... Oh , Jesus . - You just touched her .
My fucking Christ , you just touched her face .
I touched her head , the top of her head .
Watch .
- ( RUBBING HAND ) - No , please , don 't do that .
( BREATHES HEAVILY )
( SNIFFS )
( CRUNCHING )
( RETCHING AND CLICKING )
( HISSING )
( SNARLING AND PANTING )
( PANTING )
( ALL START SNARLING )
( ALL GIBBER AND SNARL )
Stop it !
( SNARLING AND GIBBERING CONTINUES )
You think something 's human because it 's vaguely the right shape ?
- No , I don 't think that . - Good . Here endeth the lesson .
( GIBBERING AND SNARLING SUBSIDES )
( DOOR CLANGS SHUT )
What are you looking at ?
If I had a box full of all the evils in the world , I 'd stick you inside and close the lid .
( SCOFFS )
( CHUCKLES ) Oh , shit .
I 'd better make sure you never get a box .
She likes me best . She touched me .
She wouldn 't ever touch you .
- You 're all done here . - Sarge , wrist and ankle restraints .
Dismiss !
( LOCK CLANGS )
( FOOTSTEPS RECEDE )
( DOOR WINDOW SLIDES OPEN )
Melanie .
- Good evening , Miss Justineau . - Who did this to you ?
Hello ?
Someone ?
( SIGHS )
( KEYS JANGLE )
It was Sergeant Parks , wasn 't it ?
He did this to you .
( MELANIE SNIFFS )
Miss ... Miss Justineau , you smell nice .
- Don 't talk to him , OK ? - ( CLICKING AND CRUNCHING )
- Promise me . If you ignore him , then ... - No ! Get out !
Get out !
( SNAPPING , RETCHING AND GASPING )
( GASPING AND PANTING )
( SNARLING CONTINUES )
I 'm sorry !
( SOBS ) I 'm sorry !
DR CALDWELL : Good evening , Melanie .
- I see you had another visitor tonight . - No .
These are rationed and numbered .
I can find out whose it is by looking on the list .
I think I know who it might have been .
Would you like to give me another number ?
- Anything from ... - Four .
Number four .
Really ?
" Four . "
( LIGHT SWITCHES CLUNK )
( KLAXON HORN BLARES )
- MAN : Transit ! Let 's go ! - ( BANGING ON DOOR )
Up you get !
Wakey-wakey , we 're on the move !
- WOMAN : Come on , now ! - MAN : Transit !
- ( BANGING ON DOORS ) - MAN : Transit !
( FOOTSTEPS RECEDING )
( PANTING )
( FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING )
Good morning , Private Raison .
Good morning , Sergeant Parks .
Where are we going ?
What 's this place called ?
( LIFT RATTLING )
Why is it shaking ?
( DISTANT RATTLE OF MACHINE GUNFIRE )
( MEN SHOUTING )
Sarge , south section . Fence one is down .
Use the flamethrower . Short bursts .
( MACHINE GUNFIRE )
( SOLDIERS SHOUTING )
- Need me for anything else ? - Emphatically not .
Lock all the doors after I 'm gone , and stay inside until the all-clear .
Good morning , Dr Caldwell . Good morning , Dr Selkirk .
Good morning , Melanie .
Did you think about that cat ? The cat in the box ?
It 's not alive or dead . It 's just gone .
- DR CALDWELL : Why ? - Cats are clever .
The standard answer is , it 's both .
Alive and dead at the same time .
MELANIE : That 's stupid . ( GASPS )
DR CALDWELL : Possibly .
But it 's what you came here for , isn 't it ?
The answer to the mystery .
It 's you , Melanie .
In this analogy , you open the box and you find yourself there .
I 'm sorry .
Dr Caldwell , I 'd like to get back to the classroom now , please .
Three mil , thiopental .
( DOOR OPENS )
- Good morning , Miss Justineau . - ( PHONE RINGS )
DR CALDWELL : Helen , we are in the middle of a procedure .
Leave it . I 'm not doing this any more .
More self-doubt , Helen . We are so close .
This isn 't what I signed up for .
It is exactly what you signed up for .
We 're cutting up children .
They present as children .
You know my opinion on that .
That the pathogen , the fungus , does their thinking for them ?
You only have to speak to them for five minutes !
I do that every day . I read your reports every day .
Helen , this is an argument I 've had with myself a thousand times .
But I 'm listening .
Look , putting the scalpel down .
And you can put down your weapon .
Please .
- Ow ! ( GASPING ) - Miss Justineau !
Security detail . Go !
( SCREAMS )
No ! Leave her alone .
( COUGHS )
( HELEN GROANING AND COUGHING )
Wait a moment .
Helen , this is not another blind biopsy .
This is a processing run . Do you understand me ?
I am producing a test batch of a vaccine and she is the main ingredient .
What you 're feeling ... I respect it , but I can 't afford it .
- Put her in a safe place . - Doctor , we 're really busy right now ...
You 're responsible for her .
- ( HELEN GRUNTS ) - Miss Justineau !
( KLAXON ALARM BLARES )
Should we postpone ?
No . Drop the shutters .
- She 's moving too much . - ( MELANIE STRUGGLING )
There 's a cranial strap on the left .
I 'm not gonna cut around a cranial strap .
Do I re-dose her ?
DR CALDWELL : Yes , yes , Jean , that would be extremely ...
( SCREAMING )
- ( SNARLING ) - ( GASPING AND GRUNTING )
( SNARLING AND SNAPPING )
( GRUNTING )
( GASPING AND PANTING )
( RETCHING AND CRUNCHING )
( PANTING )
( SNARLING )
( SNARLING AND GIBBERING )
( MELANIE PANTING )
( SNARLS )
( POUNDING ON DOOR )
( SNARLING )
( SCREECHING )
( MELANIE STRAINING )
( DR SELKIRK SPUTTERING )
( PANTING )
( GUNSHOTS )
( SOLDIERS SHOUTING )
- ( SNARLING ) - Argh !
( GUNSHOTS AND SCREAMING )
WOMAN : Help ! Help me !
( SHOUTING AND SNARLING )
( GUNFIRE )
MELANIE : Miss Justineau !
HELEN : Melanie !
- Get off ! Stupid bitch ! - No !
- ( SNARLING ) - ( GRUNTS )
DEVANI : Stop !
( SCREAMING )
Fuck ! ( SCREAMS )
- ( GUNSHOTS ) - ( RETCHING )
( GUNFIRE AND SHOUTING )
( PANTING )
PARKS : Come on !
( GATES RATTLING )
( PANTING )
- ( SNARLING ) - ( SOLDIER SCREAMING )
( MACHINE GUNFIRE )
Melanie . Melanie .
Shh , come on . Shh , shh . It 's OK .
It 's OK , Melanie . It 's OK .
It 's OK .
( BOTH GASPING )
( SIGHS )
Put our coordinates out on all frequencies .
- Log it as muster point one . - Sarge !
- Sergeant , no ! - She 's not hurting anyone ! Just let her out !
- Move . - Let her out , then she 's gone ! Go ! Go ! Go !
DR CALDWELL : What the fuck are you doing ? That 's not your decision to make !
( GASPING )
( INSECTS BUZZING )
Nothing , Sarge . Empty on all frequencies .
Then we 'll leave . But I need you to retrieve the test subject .
PARKS : Gallagher , check the locker for supplies .
Dillon , cover the kid .
Don 't shoot her unless she moves .
Oi , stay with the vehicle .
No . Don 't come too close to me .
I won 't .
- Are you OK ? - I did something bad .
You did a good thing .
- You saved me like in your story . - It wasn 't like my story .
I ate bits of the soldiers .
The girl in my story didn 't eat people .
If they were coming , they would be here
or they would have answered your muster call .
What have we got ? Any water ?
The truck was in the shop , Sarge . Tank got emptied out when they cleaned it .
There 's canteens , a few clips of ammo , blocker gel and ... This lot ?
I figure it 's what the field teams used back when they were ,
- you know , trying to catch the ... - Yeah , I know what it is .
Justineau !
( SOFTLY ) Just wait here .
Right , everybody , listen to me .
We 're going south to Beacon .
We 're gonna stock up on water and then we 're off .
What about the base personnel ? The children ?
Got to assume they 're dead .
As far as the kids are concerned , hungries don 't eat their own .
Once we get back to Beacon , we can mount a search-and-rescue .
- And Melanie ? - She belongs to the programme
and she 's vital .
I would suggest you take out the spare wheel and put her in the wheel well .
- It 's an enclosed space ... - ( GRUNTS )
Was that cathartic ?
Whoa ! Once is enough .
HELEN : She 's not going in the wheel well .
I just wanted to make that clear .
No , she 's not .
( ENGINE STOPS )
PARKS : Suppressors on . Soft rounds .
MELANIE : How can bullets be soft ?
DILLON : Do you want me to gag it , sir ?
- Means they 're hollow at the tip . - Why ?
Spreads as it goes in . Doesn 't come out .
- Less blood spatter . - Why ?
Less chance of spreading the infection .
Thank you , Sergeant Parks .
Let 's move .
PARKS : Be quick .
( TWIGS RUSTLING )
- Jesus Christ , I said suppressors ! - Sorry , I didn 't ... Shit !
( RUNNING FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING )
Move . Let 's go . Go !
Go !
( SNARLING AND CLICKING )
( SNARLING )
( GUNFIRE )
( GRUNTS )
- ( SNARLING ) - ( GRUNTING )
- Sarge ! - Shit !
- Fucking hell ! - ( SNARLING )
( GRUNTING )
( SCREAMING )
Get its head up ! Get its fucking head up !
- ( SNARLING ) - ( GALLAGHER STRAINING )
- PARKS : Move ! Go ! - ( PANTING )
( GASPS )
Your arm .
( BREATHING UNSTEADILY )
That 's ... That 's not a bite , Sarge .
- I laid it open on a rock . - Stay there .
Sarge , I cut myself , I swear to God .
Wait .
What , with my fucking bollocks hanging out ? Sod that , let me in !
See , I told you , I 'm fine .
I 'm fine . There 's nothing ... Wrong ...
( GASPING )
( SNARLING )
MELANIE : He was turning into one of them .
- Like Dr Selkirk . - What the fuck is she doing in here ?
She 's got a muzzle on her face and her hands are tied behind her back .
And you 're still afraid of her ?
Yeah . And you should be , too .
Melanie ...
The hungries , they 've got this sort of disease ...
And people can catch it .
A fungal infection .
Ophiocordyceps unilateralis .
Transmitted by bodily fluids . So your bite is ...
She 's not gonna be biting anyone .
PARKS : Professional opinion .
- Were they following us ? - DR CALDWELL : Probably not .
They gather in groups , as they did in the base .
We 're not sure why .
They must be lonely .
Oh . I hadn 't thought of that one .
( IGNITION SPUTTERS )
Bullet hit the fuel line , so we 're back to Shanks 's pony .
We 'll take the direct route through to London .
More hungries , but more food , too .
- It 's a fuck sight quicker . - Seriously ?
Why can 't we just call Beacon and tell them where we are ? They can send a chopper .
I tried . The truck 's radio doesn 't have the range .
We 'll call on the handhelds once we 're closer in .
All right , let 's take a stroll .
HELEN : Come on .
MELANIE : Will we see the river ? There 's a river . The Thames .
It 's the second-longest river in England and it rises in the Cotswold Hills .
How deep are rivers ?
In the picture , The Elephant 's Child , the water is up to the elephant 's feet .
But boats sail on rivers and fish live in them , so some rivers must be very deep ...
Here . Watch where you put your feet .
GALLAGHER : They 're all over the place , Sarge .
PARKS : The shops were looted a long time ago .
We might get lucky if we go through some of the houses .
- Hungries ? - By the ton .
We 're going in .
On tip-toe .
Really ? Through a herd of them ?
Their main sensory cue is smell . The gel makes us invisible .
PARKS : Up to a point .
Anything loud , any fast movements will wake them , too .
We walk slow , steady . No talking .
No eye contact .
OK ?
( CHUCKLES ) We 're not children , Sergeant Parks .
Least of all , her .
( WHEELS SQUEAKING IN DISTANCE )
( MELANIE BREATHING HEAVILY )
( SOFTLY ) Caldwell .
- ( GASPS ) - ( SNARLING )
PARKS : Up , up . Everybody , up .
Move . Up . Up .
( SNARLING )
( SNARLS )
( PANTING )
PARKS : Be quiet and settle in .
HELEN : What ?
What else you wanna do , go back out there ?
( SIGHS )
Doctor , what was that ?
I 've never seen maternal or nurturing behaviour in a hungry .
I was gathering data , which is part of our mission statement .
It was until the fence went down .
Now our mission statement is to keep ourselves off the fucking menu .
I 'll be more careful , where possible .
( PARKS SIGHS )
Let 's get ourselves some privacy .
We 'd better do a quick recce .
Make sure we 've got this place to ourselves .
- Melanie stays here . - Private .
And someone stays with her .
I won 't have her put at risk .
( HANDCUFFS RATTLING AGAINST RADIATOR )
MELANIE : I 'll be fine , Miss Justineau .
I 'm not scared .
- Justineau , you take the left . - Yeah .
Gallagher , you take the right . Eyes and ears .
Melanie ...
If you need me , shout really loud .
Yes , Miss Justineau .
( WINCING )
Dr Caldwell ?
What am I ?
We don 't really have a term for it .
But you know where I came from ?
Tell me .
Please .
( DISTANT CLANG )
Sergeant Parks and his people used to go into the cities on retrieval runs .
On one of those visits , they found something else .
( DISTANT THUD )
( CLANG )
DR CALDWELL : Neonates .
Newborns .
Infected , very definitely . Hungries ,
but different from anything we 'd seen .
They were still able to think ,
to ...
Interact with their environment .
In many ways , they behaved like real people .
( DISTANT BANGING AND CHAIN RATTLING )
( EXHALES SHARPLY )
MELANIE : Why were the babies different ?
It seemed these children might have a partial immunity to the hungry pathogen .
But where did they come from ?
From where all babies come from .
But by a ...
Slightly eccentric route .
( DISTANT THUDDING )
( THUD )
DR CALDWELL : The newborns were found in a place like this .
A maternity hospital , where mothers go to give birth .
The mothers were there , too . They were ...
Empty .
Cored .
All their organs devoured .
- By hungries ? - No .
From the inside .
( DISTANT BANGING )
- Babies can 't eat people . - These ones did .
The mothers were probably all infected at once , in a single incident .
Then the embryos they were carrying took the infection as well ...
Through the placenta .
They ate their way out .
( BANGING GETS CLOSER )
( SNARLING )
I don 't want to be a hungry .
But that 's what you are .
In dissection , it 's very clear .
The fungus is wrapped around your brain like ivy around an oak tree .
But I can talk . I 'm like you .
You 're not like anything that 's ever existed before .
( CHOMPING )
( CHAIN RATTLES )
( SNARLS )
( SNARLING CONTINUES )
You said you could make a vaccine .
It 's the whole focus of my research .
Nothing matters more .
I want to save people , Melanie .
I want to save everybody .
( SNARLING )
( EXHALES )
I tried to find some food for you , but ... I didn 't manage .
But I did find something else .
They 're really great , aren 't they ?
Now you can get out of those stinky things .
They 're very nice .
Thank you .
Tomorrow I 'll try and find some food for you .
First thing . OK ?
Do you think you can hold out till then ?
Mmm .
( CHUCKLES )
Do you think Beacon have missed our comms yet ?
Hard to say .
They check in when they can .
They 've been stretched just lately . " Sufficient unto the day . "
What , don 't you fraternise with the enlisted men ?
You ever killed a kid ?
I was in the Terries .
I didn 't say boo to a fucking goose turd before all this kicked off .
- She looks at me like I 'm Jesus . - She loves you .
Yeah , she loves me .
I just couldn 't get out the way in time , that 's all .
I 'm not a good person .
I 've never met a good person or a bad one .
You just do whatever 's in you to do .
So no one 's ever responsible for anything ?
Responsible to who ?
MELANIE : ( READING IN DISTANCE ) " ' He 's dreaming now , ' said Tweedledee .
" ' And what do you think he 's dreaming about ? '
" Alice said , ' Nobody can guess that . '
" ' Why , about you ! ' Tweedledee exclaimed , clapping his hands triumphantly .
" ' And if he left off dreaming about you , where do you suppose he 'd be ? '
" ' Where I am now , of course , ' said Alice .
" ' Not you , ' Tweedledee retorted contemptuously .
" ' You 'd be nowhere . You 're only a sort of thing in his dream . " '
Do you want to see the picture , Kieran ?
PARKS : This does not look good .
That ruckus yesterday must have brought them .
Look , if we wait , something will turn up .
A cat or a ... Something , and they 'll run off chasing it .
We could be waiting a bloody long time .
- It 's gonna be all right . - I can do it .
No . I won 't allow it .
I 'm the only one who can go down there and not get hurt .
If we let her go , there is no reason for her to come back .
Yes , there is . I want to be with you .
- With Miss Justineau and Kieran , anyway . - " Kieran " ?
HELEN : You were gonna put a bullet in her head yesterday .
- What have you got to lose ? - I have a great deal to lose .
She is indispensable to my programme .
There is no programme any more . There 's just us .
And I 'll come back because I said I would . I don 't tell lies .
Also ...
Can I wear my new clothes , please ?
( MELANIE CHUCKLES )
( PARKS CLEARS THROAT )
( SNIFFS AND SNARLS )
( BANGS ON DOOR )
Hello ?
( GIGGLES )
Transit ! Transit ! You friggin ' abortions !
Wow .
( BOTTLE CLATTERS )
( DOG BARKS )
( DOG WHINES )
( SNARLS )
( ALL SNARLING )
( ALL GIBBER AND SNARL )
It fell off . But it 's safe to come down .
My God .
I 'm not hungry now .
Good job .
Let 's go .
( SEAGULLS CRY )
HELEN : So we 're just gonna wade in again then ?
PARKS : Not if I can help it .
Do you wanna get some more exercise ?
You can run ahead and find us a clear route .
Can I use the radio thing ?
Gallagher , give her your radio thing .
- Sarge ? - She 'll give it you back .
Right , there you are .
Show me .
Push that button to talk . Then let go so I can talk back .
( BEEP )
- ( FEEDBACK WHINES ) - It 's Melanie .
Hello , I 'm over here .
Just like that , yeah . Off you go , then .
( CHUCKLES )
Don 't play with anybody that looks dead .
She better not bloody lose it .
Hello , it 's Melanie . Melanie calling . On the radio .
PARKS : I know What have you got ?
Well , the third street 's the best one .
There 's a few hungries right at the top , but if you keep on going there 's no one .
Thank you . Over and out .
Well done .
HELEN : Do you want a cat ?
I already had one .
GALLAGHER : Fuck me .
- PARKS : Doctor ... - ( GASPING )
I saw this in Bristol .
And the team in Glasgow says it 's spreading everywhere .
It 's the next stage in the pathogen 's life cycle .
PARKS : Leave it .
This is the same thing that 's in my brain . Will that happen to me ?
Well , it depends . Do you know what symbiosis is ?
Like the little birds that clean a crocodile 's teeth ?
Exactly . In the second generation , your generation ,
the fungus may function as a symbiote .
It certainly seems to .
Let me know if you start to sprout .
HELEN : It 's gone quiet all of a sudden .
Must be the off-season .
Gallagher , don 't step on them .
HELEN : We 're never gonna get past this .
We 're gonna have to go around it .
GALLAGHER : What the fuck is that ?
PARKS : What are we looking at , Caldwell ?
DR CALDWELL : I told you . The next stage in the fungus ' life cycle .
The mature sexual stage .
This is why there are no hungries here .
When the density is the highest , when enough of them come together ...
- MELANIE : They turn into a forest ? - ( EXCLAIMING SOFTLY )
This is a sporangium , a seed pod .
There must be tens of thousands of them in that mass .
If they were to open ...
What ?
The end of the world ...
Probably .
PARKS : Let 's keep moving .
- You 're sick , Dr Caldwell . - I 'm fine . Thank you .
You smell sick .
I saw you .
You picked one up . Can I see it ?
Why would it be the end of the world if it opened ?
The hungry pathogen would become airborne .
You 'd catch it by just breathing . But look ...
( HARD KNOCKING )
It 's a bad design .
Mutants have to take the rough with the smooth .
PARKS : What the hell is this ?
PARKS : It 's full armour . Coded access .
Emergency access is under the midsection door .
- And you know this because ? - We made them .
Fully functional mobile labs .
Armed and armoured , so they could go anywhere .
Solar-powered , so they never had to stop .
PARKS : Emergency access , show me .
It 's under there .
( MOTOR HUMS )
Come on , Kieran .
( TAPS BUTTONS )
( DR CALDWELL GASPS )
Solars are still working .
See if the engine 's any good .
( IGNITION SPUTTERS )
( MATCHES RATTLE )
I need to find some food .
( CLATTERING AND BANGING )
GALLAGHER : Wonder where they are .
Maybe they went out to explore .
And stayed over their friends ' ?
( DOOR CREAKS OPEN AND SHUT )
- How 's the engine , Sarge ? - Should be able to get it working .
- Let 's try Beacon first . - ( RADIO STATIC )
Runaways from base Hotel Echo , calling Beacon . Over .
( STATIC )
Runaways calling any friendlies in the southeastern area . Over .
- Did you check out the kitchen ? - HELEN : Cupboard 's bare .
I could do a supply run , Sarge .
( PANTING )
- PARKS : OK . We 'll work on the engine . - ( VOICE ECHOING )
PARKS : Gallagher , stay close . Call in every 10 minutes .
GALLAGHER : Sarge .
( PANTING )
- What ? - I need to eat , too . I can smell you .
I can smell all of you .
( SNIFFING )
( WINGS FLAP OVERHEAD )
( PIGEONS COOING )
Right , try that .
( ENGINE TURNS OVER )
Good job .
( GROANS )
( EXHALES )
( CHILD SQUEALING )
( CHILDREN SQUEALING )
( DOOR OPENS )
( GIBBERS )
( SNARLS )
( SNIFFS DEEPLY )
( SNIFFS AND SNARLS )
( ALL GIBBERING AND SNARLING )
No . Oh , no .
( GIBBERING AND SNARLING )
( FLICKS SWITCHES )
( SIGHS )
( STIFLED GROAN )
Want me to change that dressing ?
No , thank you . There 's no point .
Is it healing ?
I 'm dying .
( CHUCKLES ) I 'm surprised you hadn 't noticed .
Inflammatory sepsis . Blood poisoning from the cuts .
I dosed up on flucloxacillin when we arrived ,
but I 'm pretty sure it 's too late .
- I 'm sorry . - How sorry ?
Would you let me have her ?
Forget it .
I was almost there when the base fell .
With this equipment , I can do it .
I can synthesise the vaccine .
But I need her brain and her spine .
Isoflurane .
Surgical anaesthetic .
She 'd feel nothing .
That 's more your thing than hers .
( BANGING ON DOOR )
MELANIE : Miss Justineau !
Kieran is out there and they 're out there with him .
They 've got his smell and they 're looking for him right now .
And you 've got to find him first .
Now ! You 've got to go now !
Melanie , who are you talking about ?
The children . They 're going to eat him .
I saw them . They 're exactly the same as me . They 're just going to hunt him down .
MELANIE : They 've got his scent and they 're gonna go and find him .
- He 's got blocker on . - Blocker 's got a smell , too .
It 's nasty , but if you know what it means , you can follow it .
How would they know what blocker smells like ?
Isn 't it obvious ?
Gallagher , what 's your position ? Over .
( OVER RADIO ) Gallagher , could you call in with your location , if you can ? Over .
Gallagher , call in with your location if you can . Over .
I could find him . Please .
Let 's head out with her .
WOMAN : ( OVER RADIO ) This is Beacon . Do you copy ?
- Here . Copy . - Confirm status . Over .
Uh , London . North of the river . About a day away from Beacon . Over .
Confirm status of base Hotel Echo .
We need to start evacuating our people while we still can .
The fences are coming down .
( BREAKING UP ) It 's only a matter of hours before they 're inside the complex .
( TRANSMISSION BREAKS UP )
- Beacon , this is ... - We 've got to go , Sergeant .
We 've got to go now !
- Beacon , this is ... - We 've got to go ! We 've got to go now !
It 's Kieran !
( SNIFFING )
He was here lots of times .
( SNIFFS )
He doubled back . ( SNIFFS )
That way !
Come on .
( FAINT CLATTER )
- ( SNARLS ) - Hey .
What 's your name , then ?
Is , er , is that yours , is it ?
No , I 'm ... I 'm ... No , I 'm good , er ...
I 've , er ... I 've had my dinner . Yum-yum . Full .
Fucking hell , look , you need it more than I do . Look at you .
You 're all skin and bone .
All right , all right .
It 's all right . Hey , it 's all right .
Come here .
It 's all right .
Look , I 'm not ... It 's all right .
Don 't be daft . It 's all right . Come here .
Come here . Look , I 'm not playing with you . Just come here .
- ( SNARLS ) - ( GASPING )
( SNARLING )
( WHIMPERING )
( HYPERVENTILATING )
( SNARLING )
( SCREAMS ) Fuck ! Fuck .
You see this ?
( SNARLING )
You fucking see it ? ( IMITATES EXPLOSION )
( SOBS )
I mean it ! You touch me and I 'll blow you all to fuck , do you understand ?
No , I mean it , I will !
( STUTTERS ) Please .
- No , please ! - ( SNARLING )
( SCREAMING )
( ALL SNARLING )
( SNIFFING )
Help me get this up .
( ALL STRAINING )
Little fuckers .
- Dirty little fuckers ... - MELANIE : They just want to live .
Everyone wants that .
You know what this is ?
They set a trap for him , the same way you 'd trap an animal .
Miss Justineau ...
This is a trap , too !
( SNARLING AND GROWLING )
( SNARLING )
Sergeant , let me ! Put it down .
( EXCLAIMS )
( SNARLING )
( YELLING )
( SNARLS )
( GRUNTS )
Melanie !
( ALL SNARLING )
( STRUGGLING )
( SNARLS )
( SCREAMS )
( CONTINUES SCREAMING )
( PANTING )
( SCREAMS )
( TRIUMPHANT SCREECH )
Miss Justineau ! Sergeant !
( SNARLS ) Don 't look at them !
- ( GIBBERS ) - Shut up !
Just at me !
( SCREAMS )
- Pretend you 're really scared of me . - " Pretend " ?
( SNARLING )
Go . Quick , go !
They 're mine ! You can 't have them !
If you try ...
( QUIETLY ) Hurry up .
Well , you 'd just better not !
( SCREAMS )
( SCREECHES )
HELEN : As soon as we get in , we hit the road , right ?
First things first . If Beacon 's relocating , we need coordinates .
Yeah , we need to tell them that Hotel Echo isn 't there any more .
Is there somewhere else , another field base close enough for us to get to ?
Shit , why has she left the doors open ?
( GAS HISSING )
( PANTING )
Caroline . What are you doing ?
( COUGHING AND SPLUTTERING )
( WHIRR OF MACHINERY )
( GRUNTS )
( PANTING )
( STRAINING )
( MOANING )
( SHRIEKS WITH PAIN )
( PANTING )
( SCREAMING )
( STOPS PANTING )
( PANTING )
I 'm much faster than you , Dr Caldwell .
If you try to cut me , I 'll bite you .
I don 't think you 'd like that .
I don 't need to breathe as often as you do .
Out on the base , I used to hold my breath and count to 1,000 .
( CALDWELL SIGHS )
The fungus metabolises your oxygen for you .
Probably we 're symbiotes , like you said .
Melanie ...
You 're a clever girl .
- I think you know ... - You think you can make a cure out of me .
I can .
I can do it right here . I have everything I need .
A cure to save Helen
and Sergeant Parks .
And Kieran .
Kieran 's dead .
But the others .
Melanie ,
only the second generation can be like you .
Would you want to see Miss Justineau turn into a monster , an animal ?
- No . - Of course not .
And it 's up to you .
You can give her something that nobody else can .
A long , full life .
Safe .
Surrounded by people who love her .
She can be safe in Beacon .
Beacon is falling apart . You heard .
- But she can go somewhere else . - And when the pods open ?
They won 't , you showed me .
( CHUCKLES ) You can 't break them open with your hands ,
but they respond to heat or moisture .
One flood ,
one brushfire ...
I promise ,
it won 't hurt .
Will you tell her ?
She 'll know you did it for her .
I need you to lie down . ( SNIFFLES )
What about the children , Dr Caldwell ?
Melanie , lie down , please .
I don 't have long . If I don 't do this now ...
" Subject 's responses . Exquisite mimicry of observed behaviours .
" Question mark . "
Do you still think that , Dr Caldwell ?
- Melanie , I ... - Do you ?
No .
We 're alive ?
Yes .
You 're alive .
Then why should it be us who die for you ?
( CLOSES VELCRO ON SHOES )
Stay here .
If you stay here , you 'll be safe .
Melanie .
- ( MATCHES RATTLE IN BOX ) - Melanie .
( GASPS )
( GROANS )
( GROANING )
( PANTING )
( HUNGRIES GIBBERING AND SNIFFING )
( SNARLING AND GIBBERING )
( ALL SNARLING )
( PODS POPPING )
( PODS CONTINUE POPPING )
( PARKS COUGHING AND PANTING )
MELANIE : You should have stayed inside , in the lab .
PARKS : I was looking for you . ( COUGHS )
- Is Miss Justineau with you ? - She 's back there .
- With the airlock closed ? - Yes .
Melanie , what is this ?
It 's seeds . The seeds that make people into hungries .
Jesus fucking Christ .
- I 'm sorry , Sergeant . I 'm so sorry . - ( PARKS PANTING )
What did you do ?
I made the pods open .
Oh , Jesus Christ .
It 's going to be all right .
No . It 's over . It 's all over . ( SPITS )
It 's not over . It 's just not yours any more .
But I thought you 'd be safe .
I made sure you 'd be safe . I closed the airlock .
( COUGHS )
( PANTING )
( LABOURED BREATHING )
Melanie ...
( STRAINING )
I don 't want to end up like them .
Please .
Please !
( PANTING AND GROANING )
Where did you learn that ?
I watched you .
Of course you did .
( GASPS )
( SPUTTERS )
( BREATHING HEAVILY )
The last time ...
Last time I ever saw her ,
she was seven months .
She was as big as a house .
She looked beautiful .
Beautiful . ( SOBS )
( PANTING ) I had to hope that
she was out there , somewhere .
( GASPS AND GROANS )
- ( GUNSHOT ) - ( PARKS STOPS STRUGGLING )
( TEARFULLY ) Transit .
( COUGHS )
Oh , my God .
( KNOCK ON DOOR )
Good morning , Miss Justineau .
Morning , Melanie .
- Down ! - ( OVER TANNOY ) Good morning , class .
ALL : Good morning , Miss Justineau .
- Get down ! - ( SNARLING )
Okay , so we 're gonna continue with ...
( SNARLING AND SCREAMING )
Okay , we 're gonna continue with getting the new kids up to speed .
Everyone else , if you can just be patient while they catch up with us . Okay ?
MELANIE : Can we have stories ?
Later . If there 's time .
There 'll be lots of time .